<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The groans of Kent: or, An humble remonstrance from divers well-affected in the county of Kent. To His Excellency the Lord Generall Fairfax, and the army under his command.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2057</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E453_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204919</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864367</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864367</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116595</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85732)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116595)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 72:E453[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The groans of Kent: or, An humble remonstrance from divers well-affected in the county of Kent. To His Excellency the Lord Generall Fairfax, and the army under his command.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G.W. neer the Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kent (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116595:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Groans of Kent: OR, An Humble REMONSTRANCE from divers well-affected in the County of KENT. To His Excellency the Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and the Army under his Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>G. W.</hi> neer the Exchange.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116595:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Groans of Kent:</hi> OR, An Humble Remonſtrance from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers well-affected in the County of KENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">To his Excellencie the Lord Generall <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and the Army under his Command.</head>
            <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the preſſures, miſeries, diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and troubles of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, our tedious and waſting Wars, with the ſad effects and conſequences thereof, the loſſe of Trade, Treaſure, and Blood, the bitter and lamentable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of poor widowes and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, eſpecially in our own Countie, and which is moſt piercing, the ſad Omens of future troubles yet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending, the returning of the clouds again after the rain; as they call upon us to humble our ſelves under the Almighty hand of God, ſo they provoke us humbly to addreſſe our ſelves unto your Excellencie, and the Honourable Army under your Command, as the hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful inſtruments (under God) of a ſeaſonable deliverance from our preſent miſeries, and timous reſtauration (if the Lord will) unto our former felicity, that the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, taxations, and vexations of our Engliſh Nation (through an Arbitrary and Tyrannicall adminiſtration of rulers) were great and manifold before this preſent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116595:3"/>Parliament began, was the complaint of all; that a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Parliament (our wonted refuge in ſuch caſes,) would certainly relieve us, was the hopes of all; that the Proteſtations, Promiſes, Engagements, Vows, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, moſt happy beginnings, and proſperous proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of this Parliament above all others, would make us a happy and free people, was the beliefe of all; but through the juſt and righteous judgement of God, and the unjuſt and unrighteous proceedings of men, even of our own native people, of ſome by force and violence, of others by fraud and deceipt, our expectations lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, our hopes periſh, our eſtates impair, our treaſure waſts, our blood runs out, our liberties are enthral'd, our priviledges threatned, our oppreſſions multiplied, our task-maſters increaſed, poverty, ſlavery, and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie coming upon us like a mighty flood, and our condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion every way like to be worſe then it was before this Parliament began; in this deplorable eſtate, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but call to minde, and look back upon thoſe hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full expectations of a happy deliverance from our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer troubles by ſeverall hands, and the unhappy fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration thereof from all; we have alwayes obſerved that the moſt publike ruine, and particular intereſts, have been alwayes fomented under the plauſible, and ſpecious advantages of publike and common good; we well remember under what pretences of common benefit, Monopolies, Ship-monies, Coat and Conduct-monies, oppreſſing Courts of Star-Chamber, high Commiſſion, Ceremonies, Altars, Liturgies, and many other oppreſſions and grievances, in matters both of Church and State were impoſed upon us; we cannot forget the primitive zeal, the profeſt reſolution, and moſt promiſing beginnings of this preſent Parliament, in delivering the Nation from theſe ſore and miſerable preſſures, together with the voluntarie and free Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution of monies, horſe, plate, ſervants, children, yea, and very lives of the wel affected of the Kingdom in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116595:3"/>Parliaments aſſiſtance unto theſe ends; together with the ſeverall Proteſtations, Oaths, Vowes, Covenants, and mutuall Declarations of Parliament and People, to live and die each with other in the mutuall preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion each of other againſt the common enemy, all ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie and oppreſſion whatſoever, as alſo the moſt wonderfull ſucceſſes, deliverances, and victories, which by the right hand of the moſt high, have been wrought for us, the many and formidable Parties and Armies of the enemy broken to pieces, their multi-forme, ſecret, and bloody plots. Councels, Contrivances, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, through the mercie and goodneſſe of God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving abortive and ſucceſsleſſe: but that which is as a ſword, piercing through our very ſouls, is this, That after 7. years labour and travell in fire and blood, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy fully ſuppreſt and vanquiſhed, all his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies broken in pieces, his ſtrong Holds and Garriſons reduced, we expected to reap in joy what we had ſown in tears, yea, in blood, which (our record is on high) was not the lives and eſtates of our enemies, but that juſt liberty and freedome of this Nation, which is their naturall, native, and proper right and due, ſo often, ſo zealouſly, ſo effectually promiſed unto us by our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament, who did frequently engage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that upon our endeavours to aſſiſt them in the common cauſe of the Kingdomes intereſt, they would make us as happy, and free a people as any Nation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heavens, yet notwithſtanding all advantages adminiſtred for the performance thereof, not only theſe promiſes are not performed, our hopes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations fruſtrated, but the oppreſſions, taxations, and troubles of the land in generall, are multiplied, the well affected party in ſpeciall is moſt of all moleſted, and vexed, the diſaffected, viz. Commiſſioners of Array, &amp; thoſe that have been notorious enemies to the Parli. evidencing the ſame by their actuall endeavors in Arms againſt the Parliament, and by their voluntarie aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116595:4"/>with monies, horſe, plate, &amp;c. admitted for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty Lieutenants of the Counties, and ſo betruſted with the Militia, and into ſeverall Committees, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and places of truſt, by means whereof, the well-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected party is moſt of all oppreſſed, vexed, and grieved in all the parts of the Kingdom, and that in a way of revenge, for aſſiſting the Parliament in the late Wars, common juſtice obſtructed, the cry of the poor, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, the widow, and oppreſſed of the land, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the male-adminiſtration of juſtice and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the complaint of all, as loud, as ſtrong and piercing in the ears of God and men, as in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this preſent Parliament; the Peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Kingdom not only unſetled, but new and thick clouds of blood ariſing from ſeverall parts and Counties of the Kingdom, through that generall diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per every where abounding, do ſtill threaten more ſtorms of blood and War, even unto our utter ruine and deſtruction; we have oftentimes addreſſed our ſelves in humble Petitions and Repreſentations of our grievances unto the Parliament, where (we confeſſe) we have had candid receptions from time to time, with many fair, and moſt acceptable promiſes of a ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able relief, yea, and ſometimes Votes, Orders, Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and Ordinances, giving us very great hopes hereunto; but alas (though we forget not the many good things done for us in the beginning of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) yet of late what have all our indeavors been unto us, but as ſowing the wind, and reaping the whirlwind; our labours of this kinde proving unto us not only vanity, but vexation of ſpirit; for when we have expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the actuall performance of theſe Parliamentarie Promiſes, Votes, &amp;c. we have met with contrary Votes; Orders, and Ordinances, deſtroying thoſe hopes and expectations which were begotten in us by their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer expreſſes; by means whereof, the Parliament of England, the wonted terrour of evil doers, (though
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116595:4"/>ever ſo great,) the relief of the oppreſſed, (though evers ſo mean) and the joy of the whole Kingdom, is ecome the deriſion of Delinquents, the grief of the innocent, and the complaint of all; In this condition, let not your Excellency be offended, if we humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minde your Excellency, and moſt Noble Officers and ſouldiers under your Command, of your moſt worthy and acceptable Declarations, Propoſals, Promiſes, and Engagements, which you were pleaſed alſo to make upon the earneſt Solicitations, Petitions, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the well-affected in ſeverall Counties, for the reliefe of the oppreſſed, the freedome of the Nation from its grievous preſſures, the juſt ſatisfaction of all intereſts, and the ſettlement of the Peace and quietneſſe of the Kingdome; nevertheleſſe even here alſo our hopes, raiſed up by the publick expreſſes of your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, and your Army, have been (if not altogether fruſtrated) yet abundantly deferred, making our heart ſick, and dejecting the ſpirits of thoſe that did undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly expect the performance thereof; notwithſtanding when we conſider,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Your endeavors to procure the accompliſhment of thoſe things in a Parliamentary way, to the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all, and ſtopping the mouth of ſcandall.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That nothing hath yet been done by your Excellency and Army (at leaſt to our knowledge) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant with, and contrarie unto the aforeſaid Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Purpoſes, and Engagements.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That neither your Excellencie, nor Army, have made a prey upon the eſtates and treaſure of the Kingdom, or any part thereof, though many opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities hereunto have been frequently offered, which we may ſpeak without the leaſt ſuſpition of flattery, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the generall acknowledgement, even of the worſt of your enemies; no Officers in your Army that ever we heard of, found guilty ſo much as of a falſe muſter, to the everlaſting honour of your Army.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116595:5"/>
            <p>Fourthly, Your conſtant love, care, and faithfulneſs to the Peace and welfare of the Nation; as heretofore, ſo eſpecially of late, eveidenced by the readineſſe, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and willingneſſe of your Excellencie, and your Army, (notwithſtanding all diſcouragements, affronts, reproaches, diſhonour, and abuſes many wayes offered, and the perſonall diſeaſes and diſtemper of your own body) to interpoſe between the Peace and welfare of the Kingdom, and the malicious enemies thereof, who roſe up like a Lion out of the thicket, and like ſo many Bears robbed of their whelps, making ſeverall inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, openly committing murthers, felonies, riots, and treaſons in the great City, and in ſeverall parts of the Kingdom, as in the North, in Wales, Eſſex, and in our own County, which had they not been ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt by the bleſſing of God, through the courage and faithfulneſſe of your Excellency, and Army, the City and Kingdom had either been in blood, or (which is as bad) at the cruell mercies of bloody and violent men, whoſe deſign was doubtleſſe the utter extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the very life, and power of Religion, and juſt Liberty from amongſt us, and to have made all honeſt and conſcientious men, however diſtinguiſhed, the objects of their revenge, rage, and furie, the moſt profane and malignant ſort of people being the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt agents in theſe tumults, (unto whom the profeſſion, and much more the practiſe of godlineſſe under any form of Diſcipline whatſoever is an Abomination) which labour of love the Lord reward ſeven fold into the boſome of your Excellencie, and Armie; and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver adored and magnified be that wiſdome of the only wiſe God that prevented your disbanding contrary to the wiſdome of men, and reſerved you for ſuch a ſeaſon as this was; for we are now fully convinced of that hand of Grace and Mercy which ſo ordered your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in Arms.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116595:5"/>
            <p>The conſideration of theſe things moſt Noble Sir, hath ſtrengthned our hearts and hands once more in our moſt humble addreſſe unto your Excellencie and youe Army, to pray and beſeech you upon all the bands of Charity, mercy, and compaſſion to your owne native Countrey upon all Parliamentary Conjurations, Declarations, Vows, and Covenants, impoſed upon you to defend the peoples juſt Rights and Liberties, upon all your printed and publiſhed Declarations, Engagements, promiſes, &amp; reſolutions upon all the Victories, ſucceſſes and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of God for you heitherto, in your upright endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for the common good, to aſſert the Liberties, and juſt intreſt of an oppreſſed people; your owne Brethren and Countriemen againſt the Tyranie cruelty, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of any party or parties whatſoever to ſollicet the Parl. (by all juſt wayes and to lay forth your ſelves to the utmoſt of your power in the ſpeedy ſettlement of this diſtemper, and afllicted Nation. Give us leave we humbly beſeech you, to dictate to your Excellencie: our humble thoughts of the moſt hopefull and promiſing meanes hereunto, and that (wee conceive) is the ſpeedy determination, and happy iſſue of theſe 4 things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>The Differences touching the King.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>The Securing the Militia of the Kingdom in faithfull hands.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>A juſt and prudent framing an act of Oblivion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>The juſt ſatisfaction of all intreſts.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>FIrſt concerning the intereſt of the King, be pleaſed to call to minde, your owne exprſſieons, printed and publiſhed to the world, filling the hearts of the Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and perplexed people, with the expectation of your actions accordingly.</p>
            <p>In your Declaration and propoſals of the 14. of June 1647. tendered to the Parliament, and printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to the world, you have theſe words. <hi>When his Majeſty in theſe things</hi> (having propoſed ſeveral good
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116595:6"/>things for the publike <hi>peace and benefit</hi>) <hi>and what elſe ſhall be propoſed by the Parliament neceſary to ſecure the rights, and Libertyes of the people; and for ſetling the Militia and peace of the Kingdome, ſhal have given his concurrence to put them paſt diſpute, wee ſhal then deſire that the Rights of his Majesty and his poſterity, may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered of, and ſetled in all things ſo far as may conſiſt with the Rights and freedome of the Subiect, and with the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſame for the future.</hi> And in your Declaration of the 2. of Auguſt 1647. <hi>And to theſe propoſals which we here firſt tendred, as neceſſary to a peace, and upon which wee deſire a ſeale of prace in the reſtitution of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and others to their rights, and in an act of oblivion to be paſt &amp;c. And in your propoſalls of the</hi> 1 <hi>of Auguſt</hi> 1647. <hi>in the</hi> 14 <hi>head of thoſe propoſals thus. That the things here before propoſed being provided for the ſetling and ſecuring the Rights, Liberties, Peace, and ſafety of the Kingdom, His Majeſties Perſon, His Queen, and Royall Iſſue, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to a condition of ſafety, honour, and freedom in this Nation, without deminution to their perſonall Rights<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or further limitation to the exerciſe of the Regall power, there according to the particulars aforegoing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe ſeveral promiſes and ingagements of yours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the King, give very great ſatisfaction to the wel-affected of the Kingdoms, and did put them into great expectations of the ſpeedy performance thereof. We cannot conceive how the peace of the nation can bee ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and the differences, diſtempers, and jealouſies of the people compoſed, untill the differences between the King and people bee (by ſome juſt and ſafe way) deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined; for heare the flames of war at firſt broak out, and the fire (though ſeemingly quenched) will from hence (except timely prevented) kindle into higher flames of warre and deſtruction. It cannot be our rationall deſire, that the King (or any others) ſhould be advanced to the hurt, prejudice, and vaſſallage of the people; we know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that there is no prerogative or priviledge of King
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116595:6"/>or Parliament, which is inconſiſtant with the juſt liberty and welfare of the people; we would therefore much rather chuſe an everlaſting warre, then everlaſting bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and ſlavery, as conceiving it more ſntable to the principles of piety and humanity.</p>
            <p>And we humbly pray that the Parliament may be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by you, that our Covenant (ſolemnly made, with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> our hands lifted up to heaven, thereby calling the great God of heaven and earth to witnes for our ſincerity, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying his divine aide for performance) was not made to King or Parliament: but to God the judge of all; And that therefore neither King, nor Parliament, can abſolve us from the obligation of it; as therefore we were drawn into this bond at the inſtance, by the convincing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and good example of the Parliament: ſo we hope the Parliament will not commit ſo great wickednes, as to become Covenant breakers with their God them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, much leſſe require others, and leaſt of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them to it, and thereby bring an heavy curſe upon the whole Kingdom. Which yet, if they ſhall do, (and which our gratious God forbid) we (knowing the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the Almighty) beſeech you to declare (in our behalfe, that we cannot, we dare not, nay we will not joyne, or conſent with them therein. Pardon us if again we beſeech your Excelencies endeavours in ſetling the great buſineſſe of the King, by ſome juſt and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous way: Let the people know what they ſhall truſt unto and not be thus harraſed by perpetuall troubles, and warre, as they are like to be if this buſineſſe be not determined.</p>
            <p>And in caſe his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſhal refuſe to give ſatisfaction to theſe juſt demands of the people, and ſo continue the Kingdom in this ſad, unſetled raging diſtemper, ſo that we cannot enjoy peace and truth in ſecurity with him, (whoſe juſt rights together with our own we hartily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire) then we intreate that the Parliament may be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of their moſt reaſonable and equall votes which they have made, and publiſhed to the world in print, viz.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116595:7"/>
               <hi>To ſetle the Kingdom without him.</hi> And our further hopes and deſires to your Excelency and honorable Army are, that (untill theſe things before mentioned ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, one way or other) you will not lay downe Arms, nor ceaſe to uſe all juſt endeavours, according to thoſe vowes and ingagements that lye upon you.</p>
            <p>And the ſence of our own engagements together with your ſelves hearin, enforce us to declare that we muſt, and ſhall ſtand by you with our lives and fortunes, in the ſpeedy proſecution hereof, as chooſing rather to die a thouſand deaths, and to hazard the diſpleaſure of all men in the world, then to be found falſe in the Covenant of our God, and ſo draw down divine vengeance on us and our poſterity. And becauſe the future peace and welfare of the Kingdom cannot be ſecured, except the Militia thereof be intruſted into ſafe hands.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place wee humbly requeſt, and beſeech your Excelency and Army, to call to mind the ſecond &amp; third heads of the Propoſals of your Excelency and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, of the firſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1647. concerning the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Militia of the Kingdom both by Sea and Land, &amp; the many particulars hereunto belonging (to long to be here inſerted) that the ſaid Militia may not be truſted in the hands of any but thoſe, that have given moſt palpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble evidence of their good affections to the common care, againſt the common enemy nor declined ſince in their faithfulneſſe, as ſome moſt baſely have done.</p>
            <p>And (that every root of bitternes, wars and diviſions may be plucked up) in the third place wee humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire your Excelency and Army, to take againe into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration the eighth particular of the Declaration, and Repreſentation of your Excelency and Army of the 14. of <hi>Iune</hi> 1647. in theſe words, <hi>That publick juſtice being firſt ſatisfied, by ſome examples, of the worſt of excepted perſons, and other delinquents having paſt their compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſome courſe may be taken by a generall act of oblivion or other waies, whereby the ſeeds of future warre or fears,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116595:7"/>either to the proſent age, or poſterity, may the better be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, by eaſing the ſence of preſent, and ſatisfying theſe fears of future ruin, or undoing to perſons or families who may drive men into any deſperate wayes for ſelf preſervation or remedy, and by taking away the private remembrances, and diſtinction of perſons, as far as may ſtand with ſafery to the rights and liberties we haue hithers a fought for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo the 16 head of your Excelencies and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Propoſals of the firſt of Auguſt 1647 in theſe words <hi>That there may be a generall act of oblivion, to extend to all, (except the perſon: to be continued in exception) to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve from all treſpaſſes, miſdemeanours &amp;c. done in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of the war, and from all trouble or prejudice for or concerning the ſame, after their compoſitions paſt, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them to all priviledges &amp;c. belonging to other ſubjects provided as in the fourth Article, under the ſecond generall head afore going concerning ſecurity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fourth place (the ſeeds of future wars being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away) that all intereſts may be ſatisfyed, we deſire your Excelency and Army to reconſider, what you were pleaſed to remonſtrate to the Commiſſioners as St-<hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans Iune</hi> the 23. 1647. to be by them humbly preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Parliament; You are pleaſed to declare for the King and his party (ſo far as can conſiſt with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right or freedom, and with ſecurity of the ſame for future) in theſe words, <hi>And we do further clearly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, we do not ſe how there can be any peace to this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom firm and laſting, without a due conſideration of, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the rights quiet and immurity of his Maj ſties Royall family, and late partakers, and herein wee think that tender and equitable dealing (as ſuppoſing their caſes had been ours) and a ſpirit of Common love and juſtice dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing it ſelf to the good and preſervation of all, will make up the moſt glorious conqueſt over our hearts (if God in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſe it good) to make them and the whole people of the land laſting freinds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for ſatisfaction in matters of Religion, you have
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116595:8"/>been pleaſed to declare, (and we truſt in the true and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al purpoſes of your hearts) in your Declaration and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the 14. of June 1647. in theſe words. <q>And whereas it ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h been ſuggeſted or ſuſpected, that in our late or preſent proceedings, our deſign is to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow Presbytery, or hinder the ſettlement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to have the Independent Government ſet up, we do clearly diſclaim and diſavow any ſuch deſignes; we only deſire, that according to the Declarations promiſing a proviſion for tender Conſciences, there may ſome effectuall courſe be taken, according to the intent thereof; and that ſuch who upon conſcientious grounds, may differ from the eſtabliſhed formes, may not (for that) be debared from the common rights, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties or benefits belonging equally to all as men, and members of the Common-wealth, while they live ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, honeſtly, and inoffenſively towards others, and peacefully and faithfully towards the State.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now may it pleaſe your Excellency, and Honourable Army, theſe things and many others of the like nature, you have been pleaſed (we truſt) to repreſent and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to the world, with a true and real intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of heart (and not to ſerve a preſent turn) that you might perform, and by all juſt wayes put the ſame in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, notwithſtanding thoſe clamorous objections, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and accuſations caſt upon you by the ignorance of ſome, and mallice of others, that you ſhould take upon you the ordering of the Parliament, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdom by the power of the Sword, the Parliament it ſelfe having often taught us, as you well obſerve in your Declaration of the 14. of June 1647. in theſe words, <q>the Parliament hath declared it no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of Magiſtracy to ſide with the juſt principles and law of nature and Nations, being that law upon which (you ſay to the Parliament) we have aſſiſted you, and that the Souldiery may lawfully hold the hands of the Generall who will turn his Cannon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116595:8"/>his Army on purpoſe to deſtroy them; the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men the hands of the Pilot, who wilfully runs the Ship upon a Rock, (as out brethren of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <hi>Scotland</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who were juſtified and protected by their own and this Kingdom, when in the firſt begining of their late differences aſſociated in Covenant for the very ſame grounds and principles, having no viſible forme either of King or Parliament to countenance them.</q> For it is not <hi>Salus Regis</hi> but <hi>Regni,</hi> that is <hi>Suprema Lex.</hi> As for Parliaments priviledges, it cannot be preſumed that they amount to any thing, directly contrary to the peace and welfarre of the Kingdom, the Parliament it ſelfe, (much more their priviledges) having their very being as ſuch for the peace and welfarre of the people. Your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and honorable Councel of Warre declared in your letter to the Lord Major, and Common Councel of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> June the 25. 1647. <q>That the name of Priviledges muſt not lie in the ballance with the ſafety of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the reality of doing juſtice.</q> And in your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance of the 23. of June, 1647. <q>We clearly find, (and all men may ſee it) that Parliament Priviledges, as well as Royall Prerogative, may be perverted and abuſed, to the deſtruction of thoſe greater ends, for whoſe protection and preſervation they were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or intended; to wit, the Rights and Liberties of the People, and ſafety of the whole, and (in caſe they be ſo) the abuſe, evill, or danger of them, is no leſſe to be contended againſt, and the remedy thereof no leſſe to be endeavoured then the other.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Wee humbly pray your Excelency and Army that all due waies may be continually imployed to maintaine mutuall amity, love, and correſpondency between the Parliament, Cit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and Army; but above all that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intereſt of the people may be preſerved from the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent hands of any, and that your Excelency and Army would improve your utmoſt wiſdom and power in the juſt and ſpeedy ſetlement of our common freedom from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116595:9"/>this perplexed condition in which we are. We deſire your Excelency and Army to believe, that we are ſo far from declining the Parl. in our humble addreſſes, as that having frequently ſolicited them in our own perſons. ſo now by your Excelencies implored mediation, we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray their conſideration of our afflicted condition, &amp; utmoſt endeavours for a ſpeedy relief herein. Alas Sr. what ſhall we do? in the begining of theſe troubles he that did not ingage for King nor Parliament was puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by both (if within the reach of either) he that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged for the one was perplexed by the other, and of late the croſſe orders, votes, and ordinances of the Parliament it ſelfe, have beene ſuch that their moſt cordiall friends know not where to fix.</p>
            <p>We humbly pray your Excelency and Armies ſerious conſideration of the premiſes, and aſſiſtance in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamity, and the Lord of Hoaſts bleſſe and proſper your Excelency and whole Army, teach your hands to war and your fingers to fights, cover your heads in the day of battle, and at length give you to reape the frute of jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parding your lives in the high places, in making you the happy inſtruments in his hand of ſetling the unhappy differences of the Nation upon the pillars of peace and truth.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
